A biblical theology of generosity does not start with tithing, or even Jesus' command
to be generous to the poor.
It starts before time and space, with who God is.
Since the beginning of Scripture, the world itself was created as an act of generous love,
with God as a joyful, generous host, the world as His home, and you and I as His special
guests.
And from the inner nature of God, giving becomes our nature.
And little by little, He makes our souls incandescent.
Oh, there we go.
How's that?
There we go.
That was unmuted.
The whole time during worship, I'm glad you couldn't hear me singing.
Wow.
Man, let's all just, can we just sit here for a second?
And I want, and this is just spur of the moment.
In thinking of the last song that we just sang.
In how this crescendo of this service has been going.
Beginning with, you know, even the announcements like the administration.
But then public confession.
And then worship, and then worshiping together.
There's this deep sense of unity I really feel in this room.
And so I want us to just sit for a second.
And as we, we're gonna dig into this third week of generosity.
I want, I would implore you to maybe just sit here for a second.
And I want you to just really think of the goodness of God.
If you've never met Jesus before, hopefully you get to meet Him this morning.
But if you've met Jesus before, you've experienced His goodness.
And so as we sang about coming to the altar and the Father's arms are open wide.
I want you to just, you know, imagine yourself sitting in the goodness of God with the Father's arms.
Father's arms just wrapping around you in this eternal blanket of love.
Father, we give this, as we've already declared before, Lord.
We give this time to you, Lord.
And I just want to just partner right in with the unity in this room, Lord.
That there's fellowship in your spirit, Lord.
But your spirit is really, really uniting this body.
Lord, we're grateful for your presence.
We focus on you as our Father as we walk through this third week.
In generosity, Lord, in Jesus' name.
Amen.
If I've not met you before, my name is Nick Payne.
Some of you recognize me.
Some of you may not.
I attend a different church here in Winchester at Crossroads Community Church.
I'm an associate pastor there.
Ryan graciously invited me to come be a part of this Practicing the Way series.
And, you know, I'm very grateful to have the opportunity to join in.
I was here for the fasting practice.
Who was a part of the fasting practice?
Are you guys glad we're not in that anymore?
Bro.
But now we're in generosity, which that hits another part of our life that we need to have given over to God.
I have a, this is a, you're going to feel like this might be slightly out of place.
But I want to sort of set the stage on what my perspective is on generosity and sort of money.
When my wife and I surrendered our lives to Jesus, we literally had to give our whole lives to him.
Because we were struggling business owners who, I don't even know how we paid our mortgage and our car payment.
And our other bills on top of our employees and everything.
Like, it was hard.
And when we really got a hold of our lives in Christ and surrendered our lives, we had this wild thought that we need to calculate our back tithe.
So I was 29 when I surrendered my life to Jesus.
And I've pretty much worked full time since I was 18.
There's been pockets of maybe a month or so where I might not have had a job.
But pretty much since I was actually 15, I'm sorry, till 29 I worked.
Full time 18.
And the same with my wife.
Pretty much since high school working.
So we calculated out back tithe.
And we came up with it was less, about almost $400 a month for like 10 years we felt like we owed God.
And I mean, I'm laughing about this now, but we were dead serious.
We're like, we're going to pay back tithe.
Because we are so convicted of not giving in to who God is.
At times in our life, we would mail money to her grandmother because she was like our spiritual sort of connection at the time.
We tithe $20 to her family here and there because we just felt like we were giving to God.
So we came up with our number.
We wrote a check.
We gave it to the church.
And that check bounced.
You want to talk about embarrassment.
That like we were still sort of new to the church.
We'd only been there like less than a year.
And we had given before and those checks went through.
But this check bounced.
And that really made us reflect back.
Were we doing it out of our own will and desire, which is fine.
Or were we like out of compulsion and need versus out of the generosity of what God's actually done.
And so we didn't need a lot of discernment to see God saying, I don't need you to pay me back tithe.
You don't owe me money.
And if there was interest on that, it might have been a little higher payment for maybe 30 years.
But, you know, God is generous.
And he doesn't require things like he did under the law.
Like he did before.
There's a beautiful story in 1 Kings, or 2 Kings 22 with Josiah.
And many people see Josiah as this king that brought reformation, and he did.
But he saw this.
When they were redoing the temple, they tore down a wall, and they found the book of the law in the wall.
Which is wild that the Bible was hidden in a wall.
And then when he read it, Josiah tore his clothes, or in fact had it read to him.
He tore his clothes, and he laid on the floor, and he was, you know, just absolutely grieved at what he was hearing.
But it was called the book of the law.
And then later in that chapter, the beginning or the next, I can't remember if it's the end or the beginning.
The language changes from book of the law to book of the covenant.
And that's the perspective that we have with God.
That it's not law under compulsion, but it's covenant, which is love.
And so as you've been journeying, this is the third week of generosity.
We see God as a covenantal God, not as this law God that comes down to smite us because we've done wrong.
Amen?
So like I said, this is the third week that you're in this process of practicing the way.
And it's, who's been stretched so far?
Wow, only a couple of you?
Wow, so let me heap some condemnation this week and see if we can't get this ball rolling.
There's vulnerability that we have when we talk about this type of subject, subject of money.
You know, we don't, you know, post pictures of our bank account balances online, but we certainly post pictures of our kids and pictures of life.
But we don't post pictures of our bank accounts, but yet we can see our bank accounts by looking at people.
You even heard Ryan vulnerably share last week that in the Miller household, mattresses are important.
And we're going to spend the money on a mattress.
An old friend said, there's two things you spend a lot of money on is shoes and a mattress.
Because you're in your shoes a lot and you sleep half your life.
So you better have a good mattress.
You know where somebody's bank account is by just looking at them.
If you came to my house, you'd see what my bank account's like, that I like coffee and food.
Or you could just talk to me for five minutes and know that I like coffee or just look at me and know that I like food.
But we know where somebody's money is by looking at them.
We know where your bank account is.
And I know that that sounds strange, but that's just the reality of being vulnerable in a community like we're in.
We're in a community at Crossroads.
We're in a community of, you're in a community at Canvas.
We're in a community of the body of Christ in Winchester.
And then in Virginia, the United States, the global world, we're all in this vulnerable community.
And so we can see each other whether we want to or not.
So throughout this journeying through generosity, the first two sessions where there's more joy than giving,
that was watch out for greed.
This week, it's going to be all we have belongs to God.
And then next week, I don't know who it is, but they're going to finish it up with being generous to the poor.
And that's actually one that I think I need the most growth in, is how I am being generous to those who might be less fortunate in our lives.
As was said in previous sessions, scholars argue that upwards of 25% of Jesus' teaching have to do with money and generosity.
But almost half of Jesus' parables have to do with teaching his discipleships, stewarding their resources.
Half of Jesus' teachings were about him sharing with the disciples about stewarding their resources.
That's wild that he was having to teach them over and over and over again.
He wasn't teaching them over and over again how to pray.
We only have two times that he taught pray this or pray in this way.
But half of them were parables about stewardship.
That should make us think that Jesus was really trying to hone in on something.
The subject of stewardship is not a complicated one, yet it is deeply revealing of what we hold on to the tightest.
So this week, we're going to start in Luke chapter 12, verse 35, is what they've kind of like laid out for practicing the way.
And I'm trying to be really true to the material, but as I was studying this and preparing, I was really stuck with like, we'd start in 35, and it's like, you're starting mid-conversation.
And who knows, you always mishear something by jumping in mid-conversation.
You end up giving, you don't have the full scope of what's being discussed.
So I want us to back up slightly and start in verse 32 of Luke 12.
And Luke says this,
Do not be afraid, little flock, for your father has chosen gladly to give you the kingdom.
Sell your possessions and give to charity.
Make for yourselves money belts which do not wear out, and unfailing treasure in heaven where no thief comes nor moth destroys.
And this is sort of the hone-in part.
For where your treasure is, there your heart will be also.
So that needs to be in the forefront of our minds as we dig in to this next portion of Scripture.
It is impeccable timing that Ryan, actually I was supposed to speak next week,
but I have some travel stuff in October, so I asked if I could move to this week.
And not knowing really what this week was, and then as I started to prepare,
like man, God's really been working on some stuff deep in my heart through this.
And so I was really seeing in the impeccable timing of the Lord, which is pretty wild.
So I want us to read this one more time, because I want us to really sit in this.
For where your treasure is, there your heart is also.
I wanted this to be the first thing we hear before we go in to read verse 35 and on.
So verse 35 through 37 says this.
Be dressed and ready for service, keeping your lamps burning,
like servants waiting for their master to return from a wedding banquet,
so that when he comes and knocks, they can immediately open the door for him,
and it will be good for those servants whose master finds them watching when he comes.
Here's Jesus using this parable to teach his disciples that they're to be servants.
But there's a twist if we keep reading.
He says,
Truly, I tell you, he will dress himself to serve.
Sorry.
Truly, I tell you, he will dress himself to serve,
will have them recline at the table, and will come wait on them.
Wait a minute.
So when the master comes back,
it's not the servants that are waiting on the master,
waiting for them to come home.
No, when the master returns, sees that his servants were doing their thing,
and he was like, no, no, no.
You sit, you recline, and I'm going to wait on you.
That's a paradigm shift for them.
Think about first century people.
This is us.
We can really begin to think about whether it's some rich aristocrat that has something,
and then they're serving them.
But think about this from their perspective,
because they don't have some of the same language and things that we have today.
Jesus is telling them that, wait a minute, the master is going to be the one doing the serving.
That shifts their minds.
I'm not a gambling man, but I'm going to bet you that they were very confused when Jesus said these words.
Truly, I tell you, he will dress to himself to serve.
That means that he's not just walking to the door to serve.
That means that he's going to get changed out of his wedding garments,
because there were specific clothes that you wore to weddings,
to get into servants' garments, and then I'm going to serve.
You would think later on that when Jesus washed their feet,
they might have been a little bit more prepared for that.
But this, this even, let's keep going.
This is truly an upside down, the master role of Jesus,
totally flipping the script on what's going on
and revealing how really generous the Lord is.
We're going to jump to verse 42.
Who then is faithful and a wise manager,
whom the master put in charge of his servants
to give them their food allowance at the proper time?
It will be good for that servant whom the master finds doing so
when he returns.
Truly, I tell you, he will be put in charge of all his possessions.
So not only is the master coming back to serve,
but the master is also going to give more responsibility
to those who were found doing what they were supposed to do.
Meaning that a good job of stewarding the master's house,
the master will give him even more resources.
Think of Joseph in the Old Testament and even Daniel
in what they were given because of what they were doing.
Joseph served multiple pharaohs.
Daniel served, I think it's four kings
and or four rulers, whatever word you want to use in Babylon.
Each one of them, Daniel was promoted,
but he had to almost like prove himself back.
But he continued to serve.
He knew his position and he did it
and he was rewarded for it.
And he was always given more.
Verse 45.
But suppose the servant saying to himself,
my master's taken a long time in coming.
And then he begins to beat the other servants,
both men and women,
and to eat and drink and get drunk.
Wow.
He begins to waste the master's resources
and treats people terribly.
Jesus is really honing in on something.
Let's keep going.
The master of that servant will come on a day
that he does not expect
and in an hour he does not know
that he's not aware of.
And he will cut him into pieces
and assign him to a place with unbelievers.
Wow.
Then let's jump to verse 48.
He says,
From everyone who has been given much,
much will be demanded.
And from the one who has been entrusted with much,
much more will be asked.
You notice that I kind of skipped verse 47.
And that's because there's a lot of consequences.
There's consequences when we deal
with the resources of the kingdom wrongly.
We don't like consequences.
I mean, when I was a teenager,
I didn't like consequences
and I dealt with a lot of consequences.
I'm not gonna share with you the times
that I got in trouble as a kid,
but there was a lot.
And I deserved most of it.
There were some harsher ones
that we could argue that I didn't,
but I know what consequences are.
And there are consequences
for us stewarding things wrongly,
but I don't want us to get beat up
on what not to do right or not.
I don't want us to beat up
on what we're doing wrong.
I want us to look at what we're doing right.
What is the way to do it?
So let's keep going.
And let's jump into Jesus's idea of wealth.
Jesus is laying out in Luke 12 here,
he's laying out what I've already shared,
and it's the biblical theology of stewardship.
Stewardship is not a hard subject,
but it's a difficult subject to teach on
because I'm kind of a common sense type person.
You know, has anybody ever read G.K. Chesterton?
He's called the common sense theologian,
meaning that just do it.
Know what you need to do and just do it.
But that's not really a totally healthy view
of how to help people be formed
into the image of Christ.
What Jesus is doing here is he is exposing the disciples
to thinking differently
of what a relationship with the Lord is really like.
And for those of us that need to see God
as this like really tender father,
that's what we need to see,
and not this law-abiding God
that's coming down to spite them
for doing something wrong.
There's a quote that says,
this is how you can define stewardship
as the active and responsible management
of God's creation and purposes.
The active and responsible management
of God's creation for God's purposes.
And this idea some would call radical.
I don't necessarily do that.
I would call it just honest.
It's what we need to do.
Some say that like, you know, by reading,
or hold on.
Some say that this idea might be called radical.
I would say that Jesus' teaching,
or maybe Jesus' teaching is almost like
reminding the hearers of his words
of what was already shared throughout the Old Testament.
That to be stewards of these things,
God brought them out of Egypt.
He brought them through the desert.
He brought them into the promised land
and to steward these things along the way.
He was teaching them to rely on him
and then steward the things that I'm giving you.
Jesus is, I think he's kind of reminding them,
but at the same time, shifting some thought process
that you're not just serving God,
but God is here with you and he will serve you.
There's a few things that this is the struggle for me,
and I'm not gonna lie.
This was a hard part in these notes
that we gotta work through some tension.
Does anybody like working through tension
and not have anxiety?
Okay, yeah.
So let's just work through some tensions.
And so the first thing that I wanna say,
there's a couple of basic views
that Jesus is talking about of wealth.
And the first one is non-ownership.
Now this is, again, this is stretching even for me, guys.
I had to learn through some stuff here
and get out of my first world sort of thought
in my Western upbringing.
And so what do I mean by non-ownership?
Think of, if you've ever read Plato's Republic,
and this looks like a room of people
that have just absolutely dug into Plato's Republic.
So think about it like in Plato's Republic,
he lays out that the resources belong to society.
It's not yours, but it's society's.
But then there's also like ownership,
which is a bit of a Roman view
that it's my property.
If I have a barn, I can burn it down.
I can rebuild it.
This is mine, and you can't have it.
And that's okay.
Ownership and non-ownership.
But there's a Judeo-Christian one
that we learn sort of through Scripture
that's not either or,
but it's caretaking and stewardship.
Think about it like this.
God is the owner, and we're the caretaker.
You know, Paul's words are true
when he says in Galatians
that it's no longer I who live,
but Christ who lives in me.
Therefore, that it's like I've given up myself.
I've given up this body.
So therefore, it's not I who live anymore,
but Christ who lives in me.
Therefore, this, like God actually owns this part of me,
which there's not like sectioned pieces
that he gets to sell and buy later.
Okay, let's keep going.
God is the owner, and we're the caretaker.
Even think of the, think of,
think of Genesis, think of creation.
God creates the heavens and the earth,
and he, in the Hebrew way of saying,
the universe is creation, everything.
He creates a garden.
He literally breathes into Adam's lungs as a gift,
and then he gives the garden to Adam and Eve
to work it and take care of it.
It's like the Eden mandate,
that it's theirs to take care of.
And what did they do?
They didn't steward it well.
So what happens when we don't steward it well?
We got it taken away from us
because we didn't do it well.
Man, this is heavy.
It's okay.
I'm good.
I'm working through tension.
I hope that, you know,
if you guys have anything to talk about later,
you can, you know,
it's my email address is Ryan Miller
at Kansas Community Church.
So let's keep going.
This theme runs all through the Bible.
Leviticus 25.3 says,
the land must not be sold permanently
because the land is mine,
speaking of the Lord.
And you reside in my land as foreigners and strangers.
Then in Deuteronomy 10.14 says,
to the Lord your God belong the heavens,
even the highest heavens,
the earth and everything in it.
Then Psalm 50 says,
for every animal of the forest is mine
and the cattle on a thousand hills
for the world is mine and all that is in it.
The idea, this idea that's all the way through Scripture,
even in Luke 12,
is that God owns it all.
Sure, we buy and sell.
Sure, I own, we bought a house.
Sure, we've bought and sold cars.
Sure, we buy groceries.
Sure, we have to buy and sell.
We live in a buy and sell society,
but it's not,
I'm stewarding what God has given us.
What God has given me.
You could also say like this,
number two is,
we are entrusted by God
with resources to do good.
God owns it all,
but he entrusts us,
you and me,
to be stewards of what he's given us.
Some of us might live under this false assumption
that like everything we work for is ours.
And I'm not saying,
don't hear me as like red flag,
this is a communist statement.
Okay, I know where I live.
I know the climate in which we live in today.
That's not what I'm talking about.
That's the tension that we work through
when we hear things like this.
We are not reading political things.
We're reading the kingdom of God.
Okay?
It's not,
there's this,
like I shared in the beginning,
when we surrendered our lives to Christ,
we knew our money was not ours anymore.
I mean,
we literally wanted to pay back tithe
because we knew the importance
of where I put my money
is where my heart is.
And if I'm gonna start this journey,
if I'm going on this journey with God,
it has to be everything.
It can't just be what I pick and choose to give him.
It has to be my whole self.
So some of us think that,
you know,
we might not have the right concept
or understanding
about biblical finance
or biblical money
or what we do with our things.
I want to remind you,
and I'm gonna get off of this point.
Maybe not.
It all belongs to God.
Everything.
So some of us have to like relearn.
One of the things that I had,
we had to relearn was like
our level of living.
Had to adjust
because we wanted to be generous.
There's a story that early on again,
my wife can be a little bit of a wild card
and she comes home from a youth event
and she wants to give a very generous offering
to the ministry that we were at.
And it was $1,000.
And that was a lot of money.
I mean, it's a lot of money now.
I mean, $1,000 isn't just like
a stroke of a check in my house.
Okay, if that's easy in your house,
bless God.
But in my house,
it's still a challenge to do that.
But she did it.
And I was like,
okay, we're gonna do it.
And I don't wanna say this like lightly,
like we never felt it
because we did feel it,
but like we were never like bothered
by it financially.
Like our bank account was fine.
We paid our mortgage.
We paid our bills.
We didn't like pay that.
We didn't give that offering
and then not pay our light bill.
You know, like that would have been
bad stewardship to not pay a bill,
but give an offering.
Does that make sense?
So that's what I'm kind of trying to get into.
Like knowing where we are,
but we have to be generous.
You know, we're like right now,
this is, we have,
does anybody collect all their change
at the end of the day?
A lot of us do that.
We got this like large jar.
And the first thing Emily said this morning,
or not the first thing,
she's like, we need to do something with that.
And let's cash in and be generous with it.
Instead of like going to King's dominion,
like we might've wanted to in our 20s.
Let's save our change and have a fun day.
But no, let's be generous
with what the Lord's given us,
even if it's just change.
That's being stewards of with what God's given us.
Let's jump ahead to number three.
God blesses us to give more,
not just to have more.
You see this idea in Jesus's
parables on stewardship.
Those who the master's resources,
they did well, sorry,
those who did well with the master's resources,
they were given more to do more with.
Which seems kind of strange
that like this guy over here doesn't have much
and he's just like kind of hiding it.
And then this guy got a lot more,
but he's making more.
Like that's because he's the one over here
is actually doing something with what God's given him,
not just holding it on.
And it's not just money.
That's your own like personal talents in life.
If you're a musician,
you could teach others,
maybe not have class,
but like you lead others in being musical.
I teach some people how to cook sometimes
or how to roast coffee
or how to do the thing.
Like we are using our talents
because God's given us things to do
and we have to do something with it
or else we're gonna be like the one
that God takes it away
because we're not stewarding
what the Lord's given us.
No one does a better job
working out this principle than Paul
in his second letter to the Corinthians.
One of the hallmark passages
on generosity in the New Testament.
In it, he's raising money
for the church in Macedonia
or from the Macedonian church
to the Jerusalem church,
which is living through severe famine.
In chapter nine, he writes this in verse seven.
Each of you should give
what you have decided
in your heart to give,
not reluctantly or under compulsion
for God loves a cheerful giver.
That's probably been quoted more often
to get people to give money
than I can think of any other verse.
We're gonna joke on that in a second.
Verses eight through 11 say this.
And God is able to bless you abundantly
so that in all things,
at all times, having all you need,
you will abound in every good work
for as it is written,
and they have freely scattered
their gifts to the poor,
their righteousness endures forever.
Now he who supplies the seed
to the sower and the bread for food
will also supply
and increase your store of seed
and will enlarge the harvest
of your righteousness.
You will be enriched in every way
so that you can be generous
on every occasion.
And through us,
your generosity
will result in thanksgiving to God.
That's beautiful, man.
But there's something that has,
I don't know if it's unique
to the United States,
but it kind of is.
And that's a misused portion of Scripture.
And I'm not gonna call it a heresy,
I'll tread lightly here,
but we don't preach
the prosperity gospel, okay?
So not in the sense
of what is typically known
about the prosperity gospel
is to give to get.
You know, you give this,
you're gonna get this.
You give this,
One time we were on our,
I was planning a second mission trip
to Chile
and I didn't have the money to go.
Somebody,
I knew I was supposed to go
and I didn't know
what I,
how anything was gonna happen.
How I was gonna raise my funds.
Well,
I had this like weird,
Emily and I have this weird
anointing for people
to give us cars.
And so we've been given three cars
throughout the last 15 years.
You know,
I'm praying for the time
someone gives us
a newer 4Runner.
But we've been very blessed
by these cars
and we're still driving
two of them today.
That,
but I shared that testimony
of somebody giving us a car
because we needed one.
And then people gave
and my mission trip
was funded for.
My heart posture in that
was not,
dude,
I'm gonna share this testimony
and people are gonna give money
for me to go to Chile.
That wasn't my heart posture in it.
It was just sharing
what God's been doing
and people just gave.
But I'm sharing that
to show that like
we don't get,
we don't say to do this
to get something in return.
I didn't do that
I was just,
man,
glorifying God
and what he's done
in our life.
It was an older Subaru
that was not,
it was an old car.
It's not like this brand new,
you know,
G-Wagon
or something
that was really
had a lot of
maybe monetary value,
but to us
it had a ton of value
because we needed
the thing.
We don't give to get
and that's what Paul
is trying to say here
about being joyful
in what you give
but the Lord
will bless you
because you've given
righteously.
We're not
talking about
the prosperity gospel.
When we give
and are good stewards
of what has been
entrusted to us,
God often does
give us even more
than what we talked about.
I just shared the story.
Paul's a,
yeah.
But if you give,
God will give back
a net increase
to you in some way.
He does.
Like I said,
we didn't feel
the loss
of that giving.
We didn't feel
the loss
from that,
you know,
big financial gift.
We didn't give,
we didn't share
that testimony
to get money
in return.
We don't do this
so that God does
but he does
richly bless us
because we're walking
in like
lockstep with him.
Our lives
have to be
in lockstep with him.
My
surrendered life,
your surrendered life
is that
everything in yourself
is given over to God.
You know,
it's crazy to think
that like
your,
you know,
when we
see,
I don't want
to come across
like I'm punching
something but
can we just like,
you know,
when we give our lives
to God,
when I surrender
my life to Jesus,
you know,
I surrender
my sex life,
my bank account,
I surrender
my thought life,
I surrender,
and then the rest
of it is like
doing what we did
this morning
by confessing
the things
that we've done
and this is
the same thing.
We give,
our generosity
is given over
to God.
So therefore,
whether you give,
whether I can give
$5 this week
or $20
or $1,000
is not the matter
at hand.
The amount of money
is not what is important.
It's your heart
in how you're giving.
The position of your heart
in your giving,
are you positioned right?
It's just like the,
you know,
the parable of the woman
with the copper,
the copper coin
she gave out
of her poverty
is what the Scripture says,
not out of her abundance.
Wow.
Out of,
a copper coin today,
what would that
even be worth?
I mean,
I know copper's,
you know,
maybe that's a bad
analogy for today,
but it's not gold.
Is this tracking?
Are we rolling?
What time are we normally done?
12?
I don't believe Corey.
Can somebody else do?
Five minutes?
All right,
let's roll
through these last six things.
Because I have a big,
actually,
headline here
that says,
skip this next portion
if you run out of time.
And I think that
I've run out of time,
so I'm going to skip down.
To these six things
that are actually
really important.
And I think that's going to be
a good way to land it.
When I'm done with these six,
I'm going to invite
Marissa to come up.
All right,
so this,
our giving should be
this way.
Number one is regular
and not sporadic.
In 1 Corinthians 16,
2,
he says,
on the first day
of every week,
each of you
should set aside
a sum of money.
Now that's in their time,
that's not ours.
Everybody's finances
are different.
Some people get paid
twice a month.
You might get monthly.
You might live off
of investments
or retirement.
Everybody's different.
But the idea is
is that you set aside
what you know
you can give.
Because you know
your money,
not me.
Number two,
proportionally,
each one of us
should set aside,
each one of you
should set aside
a sum of money
in keeping
with your income.
1 Corinthians 16,
2.
We have bills
to pay.
We have lives
to live.
Remember,
it's the position
of your heart
and we need
to make sure
that we're not
just giving out
of a percentage
because the tithe
is 10%.
You know,
like,
I don't want to say
stop thinking
about percentages
because there's
a lot of financial
people that think
in percentages
and that's okay.
But so I'm just,
it's your heart,
not just the percentage.
So heart first percentage,
second maybe.
Number three,
sacrificial.
They gave as much
as they were able
and even beyond
their ability.
2 Corinthians 8,
verse 3.
It should hurt
a little bit sometimes.
We give something
every year
and we did bad
this year
and we need to actually
close it out
before the years.
We give a first fruit
offering every year
to certain individuals.
You can ask me later
what that is
but that one
actually hurts
a little bit
because that's not
normally a planned giving
and so we give
something that's,
it's gonna be
something different
but you can ask me later
what that is
because we don't have time
to dig into
what first fruit is
but it should be sacrificial.
Number four,
voluntary.
Each of you should give
as you have decided
in your heart to give
not reluctantly
or under compulsion.
2 Corinthians 9,
verse 7.
Which means we need
to make space
to pray
and discern
what we need to give.
Number five,
joyfully.
For God loves
a cheerful giver.
2 Corinthians 9,
7,
9, 7.
God doesn't want
your grumpy money.
I don't think
he needs
our grumpy money.
God doesn't need
any of our money actually
even though
he has all of it.
and motivated
by the apprenticeship
to Jesus
not religious duty
or even philanthropy.
Motivated
by being
a follower
of Jesus.
Philanthropy's great.
If you are
a donor
for the college
you went to
as an alumni,
great.
That's not what
I'm talking about.
I'm talking about
being a disciple,
being a follower
of Jesus.
For you know
the grace
of our Lord
Jesus Christ
that though
he was rich
yet for your sake
he became poor
that through
his poverty
you might
become rich.
2 Corinthians 8, 9.
Meaning that
we see growing
in generosity
as an aspect
of our training
to become
like Jesus.
Listen,
these aren't just
guides.
These are kind
of guidelines
in life.
I don't know
if you've dug
into developing
a rule of life.
Has anybody
ever heard
this word
developing
a rule of life?
Think about it
like a trellis
and a vine.
The vine grows
because it has
something to grow
onto.
So as we learn
these practices
as we become
formed in the
image of Christ
the vine grows
more because
we've set things
for it to grow
on like learning
about fasting,
learning about
generosity,
prayer I think
was the first one
that you did
this year.
These things
help us grow
and develop
who Christ
is.
But something
which is really
important,
this is a bit
of a sticky
line,
is that
without a
clear rule
to follow
means that
we have to
listen to the
Spirit of God
in our heart.
to regularly
come quiet
before God
and ask Him,
Father,
thank you for
the gift of
these resources,
what do you
want me to do
with them?
Ask God
what to do
with your
resources.
I mean,
He's not
giving us much
but I like to
give.
You know,
actually Christmas
is my favorite
holiday because
I get to give
gifts.
I like to
think about
the person
and what
they like
and then
buy them
a gift.
Not just
ask them
what they
want.
But think
about the
individual
to give
them
something.
Generosity
is sort
of just
like that.
Being
generous
with your
stuff.
And I'm
not,
again,
this isn't
some political
ideological
discussion
about like,
oh,
here's what's
mine is yours.
That's not
what this is.
And if that's
the motivation
of your
heart,
let's pray
together.
The motivation
of our
heart should
be that it
is all
God's,
all of my
life,
my resources,
all belong
to Him.
And it's
no longer
I who
live,
but it's
Christ who
lives in
me,
even through
the generosity
of my
heart.
So I'm
going to ask
you two
things.
Do you
do this?
listen to
God?
And then
maybe a
third one
is,
do you
have
action
after you
listen?
Which ties
into the
first one.
So do
you do
this?
Do you
practice
generosity?
And I
don't just
mean giving
a dollar
to the
lady
sitting
outside
of the
gas
station
on
Loudoun
Street,
although
you can.
I mean,
are you
being generous
with your
heart,
being generous
with what
the Lord's
given you,
being a
steward,
a good
steward
of what
He's
given
you?
So the
invitation this
week is
for us to
radically
rethink our
relationship with
our own money
and resources,
not as the
owner or the
co-owner,
but as the
caretaker,
to begin a
lifelong journey
of learning
to listen to
the voice
of our
loving,
generous,
and joyful
Father and
provider.
Amen?
Amen.